Okay, in this video then we
are going to discuss another
type of contract called the
time and material contract.
Now time and material contract then is
where the seller is being paid for their
time and they're being reimbursed for
their materials.
And each unit of time has a seller's
profit in built into it.
So for example then, the seller may be
charging you $200 an hour.
Their expenses are $120 an hour.
So they're making $80 an hour in profit.
So each unit of time has their profit in
built in.
So every hour, they're making $80 an hour
in profit.
And then plus, they're being reimbursed
for all the materials as well.
So that is a time and material contract.
Now, a time and material contract then is
often set.
up with a known cost, not to exceed
clause.
So if it's set up with a known cost or not
to exceed or sometimes known as a ceiling
price, then buyer and seller both have a
hand in the risk of the contract.
Initially, the contract
is going to be with
the buyer because it's time and material.
Once they hit the
ceiling price not to exceed
close, it can transfer over to the seller.
So that's what their time and material is.
You're paying the seller
for their time, and then
plus, you're reimbursing
them for any materials.
So sometimes, in this case,
then, the seller may have
an incentive to increase
cost by increasing time.
They might not work as
efficiently, right, because the longer
it takes them to do the work,
the more money they're going
to make, more profit
they're going to make.
So in that case, then,
the buyer, right, has to,
you know, control the
cost a little bit there.
But if there's a ceiling price
involved, then obviously the
seller does not want to
reach that ceiling price either.
Now, when do we prefer to use a time and
material contract?
Again, for the purpose of the exam and
from a buyer's perspective, right,
again, these are the kind of scenarios
that you're looking out for.
So you would prefer to
use a time and material
contract when you cannot
agree to a statement of work.
So a precise statement of work cannot be
quickly described or agree to.
You can't agree to a statement of work.
And for short-term staff augmentation type
projects.
Right.
So you see these kind of scenarios in a
question, right, then you know,
all right, this is going to be a time of
material type of contract.
Now, just a summary
then of all the different
types of contracts that
we've talked about, right?
So we've covered the cost reimbursable,
time and material and fixed price.
And this is, this diagram
is just basically showing
who has all of the risk
more than anything else.
So in a cost reimburseable, it's showing
buyer has all of the risk of the contract,
right?
And gradually it's going down until we get
to the seller, right?
Seller does not have
all of the risk in a cost
to reimburseable,
buyer has all of the risk.
In a fixed price contract, seller has all
of the risk of the contract, right?
The seller basically fixed price, the
buyer is just going to pay one fixed cost.
they don't really care about what the cost
is going to be.
They know they're going to pay this one
fixed price.
So in a fixed price contract, it's the
seller that's controlling all of the cost.
In a cost-reimbursable,
buyer is controlling all of
the cost, right, because
they have all of the risk.
And then in a time of material,
well, initially the risk is going to be
with the buyer, and then gradually it can
transfer over to the seller, right,
once you hit this not to exceed clothes.
Okay.
All right, so these were all of these
preceding videos then.
We were all talking about the different
types of contracts.
So remember, these are the three basic
types, fixed price, time and material,
cost or inversible, right, with some
variations of each one.